<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="https://www.slavo.me/xml/base.min.xml"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Slavo Ingilizov</title><link>https://www.slavo.me/</link><description>Recent content on Slavo Ingilizov</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 19:19:45 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.slavo.me/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Engineers should understand how their company makes money</title><link>https://www.slavo.me/posts/understand-how-your-company-makes-money/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 19:19:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.slavo.me/posts/understand-how-your-company-makes-money/</guid><description>&lt;p>Tech companies haven&amp;rsquo;t gone through economic difficulties like these for a long time. We have all heard about the dot com bubble and we know similar crises have happened, but few have lived through them. &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/4/23539737/amazon-layoffs-thousands-17000">Layoffs&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/1/17/23559412/microsoft-layoffs-job-cuts-2023">are&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2022/11/mark-zuckerberg-layoff-message-to-employees/">happening&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://blog.google/inside-google/message-ceo/january-update/">everywhere&lt;/a>. The impact of the current economic climate on the tech industry has been &lt;a href="https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/the-scoop-big-tech-layoffs/">covered&lt;/a> &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/11/14/23458204/meta-twitter-amazon-apple-layoffs-hiring-freezes-latest-tech-industry">widely&lt;/a>. Many engineers are worried about losing their job. Some of them ask their managers what they can expect from their own companies. When I hear those questions, I often realise many engineers have only a very basic idea about how their employer makes money. This isn&amp;rsquo;t surprising. An engineer can still be good at their job without grasping the intricate aspects of the business. But I think it is very useful for them to understand their employer&amp;rsquo;s business model. I should clarify that I use the word engineer very broadly. If your role is an engineer, engineering manager, delivery manager, QA engineer, or any similar role in tech, knowing how your company makes money will be very useful to you. It&amp;rsquo;s unlikely that you would be able to see a layoff coming unless you&amp;rsquo;re at VP or C-level. Having an escape plan is not the reason to do it. It helps you sleep better, but the real reason is that it opens many career opportunities for you, and it makes you better at your job.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="why-should-you-care-how-your-company-makes-money">
&lt;a class="Heading-link u-clickable" href="#why-should-you-care-how-your-company-makes-money">Why should you care how your company makes money?&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>When your work in Tech, normally you don&amp;rsquo;t deal with company finances day to day. That&amp;rsquo;s left to the Finance department or the leadership of the company if you work for a smaller one. In virtually all tech career frameworks, knowledge of finances is not a requirement for a promotion. You can survive and be good in your role without understanding that. But you can be better if you do. There are a few reasons I think all engineers should spend some time figuring this out:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#being-more-valuable-in-your-role">Understanding how you can be more valuable in your role&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#understanding-how-senior-leadership-makes-decisions">Understanding how senior leadership makes decisions&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#preparing-for-a-role-with-budget-responsibilities">Prepare yourself for taking on more senior roles with budget responsibilities&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="being-more-valuable-in-your-role">
&lt;a class="Heading-link u-clickable" href="#being-more-valuable-in-your-role">Being more valuable in your role&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>In most teams, engineers work with other stakeholders to deliver products to customers. Usually, it&amp;rsquo;s the job of the designers, user researchers or product managers to understand what customers want and decide what features need to be built. While it&amp;rsquo;s not your responsibility as an engineer to make these decisions, it&amp;rsquo;s really valuable if you can understand them and relate to the people making them. Most of the frustrations in the daily life of an engineer come from disagreeing with their team or manager. Sometimes the disagreement is about what should be built, and sometimes about how it should be built. If you have better context about how the company makes money, you can provide really valuable input into these decisions, resulting in less frustration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This knowledge leads to better technical decisions, too. When making technical choices, engineers usually are the ones who want technical debt to be on the roadmap. They are the ones who decide what framework to use when starting a project, or whether some service needs to be built upon, or started from scratch. These decisions have a huge impact on the timelines and costs of projects. Knowing how your company makes money can help you know when it&amp;rsquo;s ok to cut corners and when things should be done properly. The more directly you connect your proposal to how it benefits the bottom line of the business, the better chances you&amp;rsquo;ll have of that proposal being accepted. But to do this well, it&amp;rsquo;s key that you understand which change would bring in more revenue, or which one would be more costly. I have seen many engineers naively suggesting they take several months to completely rewrite a back-office service that has zero impact on the bottom line, without clear benefits. Not every project decision can be made based on the bottom line. Making these decisions is more an art than science and is one of the things good leaders do well. But the more context an engineer has about how the business makes money, the better their decisions will be.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="understanding-how-senior-leadership-makes-decisions">
&lt;a class="Heading-link u-clickable" href="#understanding-how-senior-leadership-makes-decisions">Understanding how senior leadership makes decisions&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>Have you ever asked for money to go to a conference, use a new tool or organise something with a team, only to be told no? Have you wondered why a leadership team might decide to do a hiring freeze or execute layoffs? In most cases, these decisions are made because the company wants to keep costs within budget. Usually the more difficult the economic environment, the harder it would be to spend money on these activities. Have you also wondered how the company decides which new products to launch, or what features to build? In most cases, this is also driven by economic reasons. Features that can be monetized take priority. Products which can bring in more revenue are more likely to be given the green light. If you want to understand why things happen (or don&amp;rsquo;t happen) in your company, understanding how it makes money can help. There are plenty of companies that brand themselves as if they are charities. They say they always do things for the customer. No matter how customer-focused and how morally good a company is - make no mistake that they always optimise for their bottom line too. Those who don&amp;rsquo;t go out of business sooner or later. So unless you work for the government or an actual charity, understanding how your company makes money gives you really valuable insight.&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="preparing-for-a-role-with-budget-responsibilities">
&lt;a class="Heading-link u-clickable" href="#preparing-for-a-role-with-budget-responsibilities">Preparing for a role with budget responsibilities&lt;/a>
&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>If you want to grow in your career as an engineer, eventually you&amp;rsquo;ll reach a level where you directly or indirectly own a budget. In these roles, you must understand how the company makes money. Your performance will be assessed depending on how well you manage that budget. This can happen in many roles even before senior leadership. Many engineers take part in due diligence on other companies (when your company is buying another one), or they manage relationships with suppliers (like cloud infrastructure providers, security vendors, SaaS tools etc.). It is good to prepare for doing this if you&amp;rsquo;re planning to go after a role with similar responsibilities.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-can-you-do-to-get-more-information-about-a-companys-finances">
&lt;a class="Heading-link u-clickable" href="#what-can-you-do-to-get-more-information-about-a-companys-finances">What can you do to get more information about a company&amp;rsquo;s finances?&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>For public companies, look at analyst coverage, quarterly earnings reports and public statements&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For private companies, look at valuations in your sector&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For your employer, ask your manager and the company&amp;rsquo;s leadership&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="which-financial-metrics-are-important-and-which-are-details-you-dont-need-to-worry-about">
&lt;a class="Heading-link u-clickable" href="#which-financial-metrics-are-important-and-which-are-details-you-dont-need-to-worry-about">Which financial metrics are important and which are details you don&amp;rsquo;t need to worry about?&lt;/a>
&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Profitability vs Revenue&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fundraises and capital vs. runway&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Hello</title><link>https://www.slavo.me/posts/hello/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 18:55:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.slavo.me/posts/hello/</guid><description>&lt;p>I had a blog before, but it&amp;rsquo;s gone. I killed it several years ago. It was one I started as a student, so most things I wrote appeared very naive and badly written. I have been toying with the idea of starting again for years now. There are things I want to say, but I never got round to it. However, the idea of writing always comes back. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those devil figures at one&amp;rsquo;s shoulder in children&amp;rsquo;s cartoons that never goes away and has an agenda. I recently went back to reading Scott Hanselman, who is one of the most prolific bloggers I&amp;rsquo;ve seen, and I wanted to figure out why he does it. &lt;a href="https://www.hanselman.com/blog/scott-hanselmans-complete-list-of-productivity-tips">Here&amp;rsquo;s what he says&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;A lot of people say, &amp;lsquo;Well, Scott, you&amp;rsquo;re doing all this stuff. Why do you do it? Are you not sleeping?&amp;rdquo; Hanselman says. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s because, I must dance. I can&amp;rsquo;t stop. Whenever I think about stopping, I think about this little boy and how excited he is about doing what he&amp;rsquo;s doing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Unlike Scott, I can stop, and I did for a long time. But doing that keeps the voice in my head and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t go away. So after a few years, I&amp;rsquo;m finally trying again. If blogging is what it takes to drive that devil figure away from my shoulder, then so be it. Here it is.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>